Guide to the Oliver Hale Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Oliver Hale papers
1936-1998
YCAL MSS 658
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.1
(8 boxes)
The papers consist of writings, a scrapbook, an interview, and correspondence by and relating to the American poet and prose writer Oliver Hale. Writings include autograph manuscript and typescript drafts of poems and other writings. The scrapbook contains clippings of Hale's printed poems from publications. The typescript interview transcript, titled "The Poet and His Wife," is an interview with Hale and his wife, Esther, by Edward R. Murrow for the radio program "This I Believe." Correspondence includes acceptance letters from publishers to Hale.
Hale, Oliver
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Philip Diamant, 1996-1998.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Oliver Hale (1897-1984)
Oliver Hale was the pen name for poetry and prose writer Oscar Hirschmann. He was born in New York City on August 2, 1897. In 1922, he married Esther Bloom, a graphologist, who was also from New York City. Hale died in California on January 30, 1984.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of writings, a scrapbook, a transcript of an interview, and correspondence by and relating to the American poet and prose writer Oliver Hale. Writings include manuscript and typescript drafts of poems and other writings. The scrapbook contains clippings of Hale's printed poems from various publications. The interview titled "The Poet and His Wife,"was conducted with Hale and his wife by Edward R. Murrow for the radio program "This I Believe." Correspondence includes acceptance letters from various publishers to Hale.
Arrangement
Organized into seven groupings: I. 1996 Acquisition. II. February 1997 Acquisition. III. March 1997 Acquisition. IV. August 1997 Acquisition. V. September 1997 Acquisition. VI. February 1998 Acquisition. VII. July and November 1998 Acquisitions.
American literature -- 20th Century; American poetry -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century; Poets, American -- 20th Century; Authors -- United States -- 20th Century; Poets -- United States -- 20th Century; Hale, Oliver; Murrow, Edward R., 1908-1965
- 1996 Acquisition, 1996, undated; 1; 0.21; (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Former call number: Uncat ZA MS 507
  - "Treasury of Published Poems by Oliver Hale," typescript photocopy, 1996 (Box 1)
  - "Published Poems by Oliver Hale," typescript photocopy, undated (Box 1)
  - "Declaration of Independence," typescript photocopy, undated (Box 1)
- February 1997 Acquisition, 1936-1983; 2; 0.42; (1 box)
  Former call number: Uncat ZA MS 512
  - Scrapbook of clippings of Hale's printed poems from 1936-1983 (Box 2)
  - "My Darling: 'O to E' by Oliver Hale and Oscar Hirschmann, 258 pages, Love Letters September 21-May 1980" (Box 2)
- March 1997 Acquisition, 1997, undated; 3; 0.42; (1 box)
  Former call number: Uncat ZA MS 518
  - General index of Hale's work, 1997 March (Box 3)
  - "Index of Poetic Estate", 1997 March (Box 3)
  - "Index of Scrapbook Poems", 1997 March (Box 3)
  - "Index of Poetic Estate, 108 manuscript original manuscripts of the 219 published poems of Oliver Hale", undated; 4 (Box 3)
  - "Index of Poetic Estate, 54 manuscript original manuscripts of the 219 published poems of Oliver Hale", undated; 2 (Box 3)
  - "Index of Poetic Estate, 259 manuscript love letters, O to E", undated; 7 (Box 3)
- August 1997 Acquisition, 1997, undated; 4; 0.21; (1 box)
  Former call number: Uncat ZA MS 534
  - "Oliver Hale, An Appreciation," typescript, photocopy, bound, 1997 July (Box 4)
  - "The Human Condition," typescript draft, photocopy, undated (Box 4)
  - "Humor," manuscript draft, undated (Box 4)
  - "Walking," manuscript draft, undated (Box 4)
- September 1997 Acquisition, 1997, undated; 5; 0.84; (2 boxes)
  - "Poetry of Oliver Hale," manuscript drafts, undated; 4 (Box 5)
  - "Indices," typescript draft prepared by Philip Diament, 1997 September 11 (Box 6)
  - "Unpublished poems by Oliver Hale: 339 Poems", 1997 September 11; 4 (Box 6)
- February 1998 Acquisition, 1979-1998, undated; 6; 0.21; (1 box)
  Former call number: Uncat ZA MS 552
  - "The Poet and His Wife" and "In Recall," manuscript and typescript drafts, undated (Box 7)
    "The Poet and His Wife" is an interview with Oliver and Ethel Hale (Esther Hirschmann) by Edward R. Murrow on the radio program "This I Believe"
  - "General Index - Rev. 'J' to the Poetic and Literary Estate to be protected, The Work of Oliver Hale, 1897-1984", 1998 January (Box 7)
  - "Prose Writings by Oliver Hale," manuscript, photocopies, and typescript drafts, undated (Box 7)
  - "Log Time and Expenses: Editing work: Philip Diament", 1997-1998 (Box 7)
  - Publisher's acceptance letters to Hale, 1979-1982 (Box 7)
  - "Oliver Hale: An Appreciation," typescript draft, 1997 (Box 7)
  - "Additional unpublished poems," manuscript and typescript drafts, undated (Box 7)
- July and November 1998 Acquisitions, 1988-1989, 1998; 7; 0.21; (1 box)
  Former call number: Uncat ZA File 391 and Uncat ZA File 398
  - "Index Item 8. The Poet's Workbook," autograph manuscript notebook, with two indices and typescript of "Poem Titles and First Lines: The Poet's Notebook", 1998 July 13-14 (Box 8)
  - "From Sidewalk, Gutter and Stoop" by Oliver and Ethel Hale, typescript (photocopy) page 510-533, with autograph letter signed (photocopy) to Philip Diamant from "Link;" with two indices, 1989, 1998 (Box 8)